<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Gene model | dictyBase Developers]]></title>
  <link href="http://dictyBase.github.com/blog/categories/gene-model/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dictyBase.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-03T10:42:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dictyBase.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[dictyBase Developers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taming the dictybase GFF3]]></title>
    <link href="http://dictyBase.github.com/blog/2012/05/28/taming-the-gff3/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-28T08:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dictyBase.github.com/blog/2012/05/28/taming-the-gff3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>dictyBase <a href="http://dictybase.org/download/gff3/dicty_gff3.zip">GFF3</a> has developed
bunch of rough edges over the years and so do not plays well with third
party tools. Here are the issues that we are aware of&hellip;</p>

<h2>Known Issues</h2>

<ul>
<li>Genes with multiple gene models could easily be confused as splice isoforms. It is
particularly hard to separate in case of known
<a href="http://dictybase.org/Downloads/alternative_transcripts.html">isoforms</a>. There is also
no easy way to identify the primary gene models.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<ul>
<li><p>Pseudogenes are not represented with proper
<a href="http://www.sequenceontology.org/resources/intro.html">SO</a> terms. The pseudogenes used
<strong>gene</strong> SO term whereas the transcript is represented by <strong>pseudogene</strong> term.</p></li>
<li><p>More than handful of assembly gap coordinates falls outside the range of reference
feature.</p></li>
<li><p>CDS features do not have a value for phase column,  which is required in GFF3
specification.</p></li>
<li><p>Missing target attribute of EST features. This is becasue the aligned coordinates of EST
  sequences are not present in our chado database,  probably left out during the
  loading process.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Possible solutions</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>The gene models will be split into individual GFF3 file for canonical, non-coding, curated and predicted gene models.
The reason for separation is that each gene model has its own customized data model
particularly the way transcripts are represented. As a result,  they have to be treated
and exported separately.</p></li>
<li><p>The canonical will be the core GFF3 with all the chromosomes, contigs and genomic sequences.
The rest of them (curated and predicted) will be supplemental and will contain only gene
structures,  no sequences and assembly features though. By default,  all
chromosomal features will be kept in a single file.</p></li>
<li><p>The pseudogene gene model will be fixed, the transcript will be
  <strong>psuedogenic_transcript</strong> whereas the exons will be <strong>psuedogenic_exon</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>No more export of <strong>gap</strong> features at this point.</p></li>
<li><p>CDS features will not be exported at this point,  would be included at a later point
  along with the phase column.</p></li>
<li><p>Rerun the EST pipeline and load alignments with EST sequence locations. It will ensure
  the presence of <strong>Target</strong> attribute. It will be available as separate alignment
  GFF3 file. However,  until the rerun is finished the existing alignment GFF3 will be
  without the <strong>Target</strong> attribute.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
